<?xml version="1.0" encoding="utf-8"?>
<feed xmlns="http://www.w3.org/2005/Atom"><title>Collected writings of Samuel Edward Konkin III</title><link href="http://www.sek3.net/" rel="alternate"></link><link href="http://www.sek3.net/feeds/abolitionist.atom.xml" rel="self"></link><id>http://www.sek3.net/</id><updated>2015-06-18T00:00:00+08:00</updated><entry><title>At the Youth Conference</title><link href="http://www.sek3.net/at-the-youth-conference.html" rel="alternate"></link><published>2015-06-18T00:00:00+08:00</published><updated>2015-06-18T00:00:00+08:00</updated><author><name>Samuel Edward Konkin III</name></author><id>tag:www.sek3.net,1971-06-01:at-the-youth-conference.html</id><summary type="html">&lt;h2&gt;At the Youth Conference&lt;/h2&gt;
&lt;h4&gt;by Sam Konkin&lt;/h4&gt;
&lt;!--FIXME: place photo here? or wait till better-quality scan is available?--&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;em&gt;we came, we saw, we converted&lt;/em&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Pleasantly surprised by the 75 degree weather we encountered
arriving at Denver’s airport, far higher than predicted, we
continue by a long bus ride to Estes Park, Colorado. After the
first night, we awoke to heavy snowfall and deficient plumbing.
Nature was foreshadowing an allegory of the White House
Conference on Youth.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;From April 18 to April 22, budding young
establishmentarians, reform-tripping on parliamentary procedure,
and a few free-loading radicals condensed from around the world
to Estes Park, the new mecca for Meeting Freaks.
Several invitations to the Conference were passed along the
spectrum from conservative to less conservative libertarians; most
invitations were ultimately turned down. Final judgement as to
who should receive the applications for invitations ended in the
hands of Society for Individual Liberty / California Libertarian
Alliance axis leadership, and led to complaints by Eastern RLA of
exclusion. Nevertheless, all three libertarians who swallowed their
repugnance of attending a purely statist function, (not to
mention repugnance of the food served there) were RLA’ers and
openly wore black flag buttons. Besides myself, Ron Kimberling
of California and Marshall Beerwinkle of Texas were present.
Two more left anarchists. Sissy Kelly of D.C. and Joost van Nimis
(International Delegate who attended Dartmouth) put on RLA
buttons during the Conference. All were on different task forces.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;At first a libertarian caucus was considered and rudimentary
efforts were made to create it. To our surprise, the formation of
an Anarchist Caucus was announced, and so, the RLA’ers trudged
through the snow to the outlying cabin where the meeting was to
be held. The meeting was called by a press delegate of a
University of California paper, and attended by &lt;em&gt;Village
Voice&lt;/em&gt; and &lt;em&gt;Rolling Stone&lt;/em&gt; reporters. No concrete proposals
emerged from the ten people there, but much joyful chemistry
was in evidence; nor did anyone stay around for the Free
Enterprise Caucus that was to follow in that cabin. Most of the
group broke off to attend the Press Conference where the
aforementioned chemistry acted as a crap-repellent. Those
interested in the details of the Press Conference can contact Ron
Kimberling, c/o CLA, Box 572, Santa Ana, Cal. RLA attendance
of the Task Force meetings with the exception of two converts,
was poor, but coffeehouse attendance, where acid rock light
shows were held, was excellent.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;The libertarian delegates spent most of their time with
delegates interested in libertarianism. Some libertarian influence
was exhibited in the Preamble and Report of the draft Task
Force. The Drug Task Force advocated legalization and regulation
of marijuana, and the right to use other drugs coupled
with &lt;em&gt;increased&lt;/em&gt; persecution of dealers, split libertarian ranks. I
made my only address to the Assembly: an impassioned attack on
regulations and control. The remaining libertarians felt their
personal safety from arrest was more important than battling for
principle, and quietly voted for the Report. No other measure
evoked action by RLA at the Conference, and voting was split on
other issues. On example of this was the Vietnam
recommendation demanding complete American withdrawal but
massive US aid in “reparations” which I felt was continuing
Imperialism in a more “accepted” guise. Fortunately another
decade must pass before the State will hold another White House
Co-opt of Youth.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;hr /&gt;
&lt;p&gt;The Abolitionist / A Publication of the Radical Libertarian Alliance&lt;br /&gt;
Volume II Number 3 / June, 1971&lt;br /&gt;
Page 2&lt;/p&gt;</summary><category term="conference"></category></entry><entry><title>Big Bang Theories</title><link href="http://www.sek3.net/big-bang-theories.html" rel="alternate"></link><published>2015-06-18T00:00:00+08:00</published><updated>2015-06-18T00:00:00+08:00</updated><author><name>Samuel Edward Konkin III</name></author><id>tag:www.sek3.net,1970-09-01:big-bang-theories.html</id><summary type="html">&lt;h2&gt;Big Bang Theories&lt;/h2&gt;
&lt;h3&gt;By Samuel Konkin&lt;/h3&gt;
&lt;p&gt;The Earth trembled. An edifice of the State shattered. And an individual’s sovereign
life ceased.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;The moment was filled with the elements of low drama; tragedy, irony, fatal error,
cloak and dagger, terror in the dark of the night, Maquis sabotage, of the oppressive
police state or a despicable act of evil by a band of crazed criminals, depending on
your viewpoint.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;The truck with the bomb was heisted from a professor known to be sympathetic to
student revolution; it was totally demolished by the blast. The call to the pigs of
warning, at 3:4O AM, was only two minutes before the premature explosion, but, even if
it had been longer, The City pigs admitted, they would not be able to warn the late-working
 Graduate Students in the physics building Sterling Hall, which is affixed to
the primary target, the Army Math Research Center. Only the University police could
warn them by jurisdiction, and they had to be contacted first. The alleged bombers, it
turned out, were assisted by the same State jealousy as the Canadian Mounties who had
them under surveillance were unable to hold them because the Federal warrants were for
non-extraditable crimes, and Wisconsin State warrants were needed.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;The Army Math Research Center (AMRC) was supposedly attacked as a tool of oppression
 of the Vietnamese people. The connection was extremely Tenuous, as the AMRC published
its work openly, and it was almost pure research. One last irony: Robert Fassnacht, the
fatal victim, was known as an opponent of American intervention in Viet Nam.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;There was dancing in the streets in the “hippie”
Mifflin Street area, followed by hot, guilty, denials
of it when the death was learned. The rest of the
reactions were horrifyingly predictable. The State’s
rulers screamed over the slap in the face—destruction
 of the State’s sacred “property” &amp;amp; incidentally,
the murder of an innocent student. Conservatives rejoiced
 in the imminent gain in votes as the September
primary approached; Liberals talked law and order defensively,
 or charged the Right with blowing up the
Center to gain from the BACKLASH. Objectivist-oriented
students wailed over the loss of research papers (which
they expected, were to be safe under the State’s protection)
 and over the loss of life. The underground
paper, &lt;em&gt;Kaleidoscope,&lt;/em&gt; printed a statement by the “New
Year’s Gang” giving their reasons for the attack—assuming
 such a gang existed. The Editor went to jail
rather than even verify the authenticity
of his article before a Grand Jury, let alone
“compromise his source of information” as he claimed.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;The RLA-symps at the University of Wisconsin had, as usual, the radical dissenting
view. “No, our erstwhile comrades in YAF &amp;amp; SIL, there was no “property” destroyed”, we
said. “And no, Weatherman, we do not rejoice at your supposed service to your pet pigs—Castro,
 Dong, et al. If a true, Free, “People’s Court” existed, you would be fortunate
to escape with conviction on charges of criminal negligence, and be justly spending your
lives reimbursing the wife and children of your “casualty”.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;For an absolute right to life has been violated. There is only one objective result
of your act. Robert Fassnacht is dead. And if there were real Justice to be obtained,
Governor Khowles &amp;amp; Senator Proxmire, you would be sued for your gratuitous smear of attributing
 this act to “Anarchists and Anarchism”. Your sudden respect for life is obscene
in its hypocrisy. We anarchists here in Madison, it seems, are the only ones left who
have consistently strived for life’s continuance &amp;amp; fulfillment; &amp;amp; we shall continue to
struggle against its enemies: the guns of the State, and the bombs of the would-be STATE. THE END.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;hr /&gt;
&lt;p&gt;The Abolitionist / A Publication of the Radical Libertarian Alliance&lt;br /&gt;
Volume I Number 7 / September, 1970&lt;br /&gt;
Pages 4, 6&lt;/p&gt;</summary><category term="terrorism"></category></entry></feed>