<?xml version="1.0" encoding="utf-8"?>
<feed xmlns="http://www.w3.org/2005/Atom"><title>Collected writings of Samuel Edward Konkin III</title><link href="http://www.sek3.net/" rel="alternate"></link><link href="http://www.sek3.net/feeds/clear-ether.atom.xml" rel="self"></link><id>http://www.sek3.net/</id><updated>2015-05-29T00:00:00+08:00</updated><entry><title>Future Societies: Libertarian Alternative</title><link href="http://www.sek3.net/future-societies-libertarian-alternative.html" rel="alternate"></link><published>2015-05-29T00:00:00+08:00</published><updated>2015-05-29T00:00:00+08:00</updated><author><name>Samuel Edward Konkin III</name></author><id>tag:www.sek3.net,1979-03-01:future-societies-libertarian-alternative.html</id><summary type="html">&lt;h4&gt;Samuel Edward Konkin III&lt;/h4&gt;
&lt;h2&gt;Future Societies: Libertarian Alternative&lt;/h2&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Suppose you are writing a Science Fiction story set
in the future. You want one or more model societies to
use as background and possibly contrast. One you
consider is libertarian. What should it look like; more
importantly, what should it &lt;em&gt;not&lt;/em&gt; resemble.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Libertarian-like societies have been presented by
Heinlein, LeGuin, Russell, Kornbluth, Anderson and
others. None were written in light of the recent
“explosion” of libertarian theory (since 1969); they
were the author’s idea of a free society independent of
the new scholarly literature and movement debates.
Circa 1969 even my own Rann Gold Series is obsolete.
One has the extreme of Larry Niven’s “Cloak of
Anarchy,” which resembles libertarian thought just
close enough to evoke howls of “smear” from the
positions attributed to the anarchists not in fact held
by radical libertarians.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;h3&gt;What Do Libertarians Think?&lt;/h3&gt;
&lt;p&gt;If you’re going to write dialogue for libertarians, you
should have some ideas of their precepts, jargons and
obsessions. I’m not going to explain the philosophy
here, just the &lt;em&gt;character&lt;/em&gt; traits. Naturally, as individualists,
 libertarians have a great deal or variety and a
great deal of differences between them, but there are
some salients in common.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;em&gt;Libertarians are morality-conscious.&lt;/em&gt; Although a free
speech, laissez-faire society is a result of libertarianism,
 libertarians are strongly concerned with morality.
Usually their libertarian position derives from some
higher precept: Natural Law, Objectivism, Christianity,
 or, in the case of the Stirnirites, &lt;em&gt;denial&lt;/em&gt; of universal
morality. Thus you could easily show a group of
libertarians in a saloon or around a campfire or in a
drawing room vociferously challenging each other in
heated debate—but turning as one in scorn on any
intruder who dared suggest resolving a disagreement
by force, then happily returning to their strenuous
arguments. Of course, some libertarians will disagree
about &lt;em&gt;this,&lt;/em&gt; and sit outside the talk sessions attempting
to achieve a mellow state.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;em&gt;Libertarians are voluntarists.&lt;/em&gt; While a libertarian
army is conceivable, and would probably be organized
as a highly efficient business company with highly
autonomous units using a high degree of independent
judgment down the “ranks,” it would exist as anything
more than a rudimentary appendix only if a clear and
present danger (large State nearby) also existed. Some
fans suggested in their fanfic a “libertarian police"
pouncing on non—libertarians, exiling them, jailing
them, or at least cutting off business with them
(including feeding and sheltering). This is as absurd
as a portrayal of a Christian medieval society with a
“Christians for Satan” club. One might portray an “ex”
libertarian society which has been taken over by
statists and corrupting the name, but they will be
recognized by many of the character is your society
(probably from the underground).&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;em&gt;Libertarians are marketeers.&lt;/em&gt; Even in the very “Left”
anarchy of Anarres, Ursula LeGuin was forced to
introduce a private press for her rebels to dissent from
the collectivist anarchist line. The vast majority of
libertarians today, even of socialistic leanings, expect
a free trade society. Most see a highly commercial and
technological organization in a libertarian society and
View the very existence of government as grit in the
gears and highly inefficient (as well as immoral).&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Any attempt at business interference would strike
your characters as counter-productive, competition
would be exalted, and crime against life and property
would arouse the populace immediately.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;em&gt;Libertarians are varied.&lt;/em&gt; While libertarians have
many rigid ideologies as well as free-form positions
there is no monolithic party line... which brings us to
the next section.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;h3&gt;What Kinds of Libertarian Societies Are There?&lt;/h3&gt;
&lt;p&gt;In &lt;em&gt;principle&lt;/em&gt; all libertarian societies are alike.
Culturally, however, one may not only conceive of
many different libertarian societies but every libertarian
 society by its nature will have numerous
subsocieties. From an SF author’s point of view the use
of a libertarian society for a setting offers the widest
latitude to the imagination. Invent any non-coercive
philosophy or religion and there’s no reason why you
cannot have several practitioners of it in your society.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;A perfectly reasonable example would be to have an
elite, Dorsai-like group of mercenaries coexisting on a
planet (a “free port” perhaps with the other planets
state-controlled) with pacifist businessmen, clannish
communal farmers, and guildish scientists and engineers.
 Throw in a libertine entertainment district,
some wandering freaks both religious and secular,
and a few refugee revolutionaries from the other
systems and presto! You’ve got more interactions,
character growth, contrasts and “conflict” than you
could possibly use, not to mention ample ideas for
humour by juxtaposition.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;In one sense, every individual in a libertarian
society is an autonomous unit. To know one is to know
almost nothing about the rest. In another sense, there
cannot be more than one libertarian Society in the
sense of distinctly separate units with defined borders
or boundaries. Anyone can go anywhere he, she, or it
can afford or get invited. Then again, one group may
decide to withdraw from the rest and isolate them—
selves anyway.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;h3&gt;No Politics, No Wars, No Taxes, ...&lt;/h3&gt;
&lt;p&gt;For a writer, conflict is especially important. Alas, a
libertarian society is particularly lacking in it. No
unemployment since one needs a minimum wage law
to keep people unemployed. No wars because you need
governments to wage them. No elections or coups
because there are no government leaders. No oppression
 because there are no police. No serious crime
because property is protected efficiently as with any
other business. No taxes because there is no government
 to collect or demand them.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Of course there are still challenges to living, over-
coming natural obstacles, making money, innovating,
personal tragedies and fights, eternal triangles and
romances, errors and corrections, inventions and
crackpottery. But if you want large scale social ills,
you’ll have to add a State or two.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;There are problems you will have to deal with
having a libertarian society bordering a statist one,
such as why the State's subjects put up with it when
they see the example of a working anarchy next door.
But one can be imaginative about such things.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;h3&gt;What Libertarian Societies Are Not&lt;/h3&gt;
&lt;p&gt;A libertarian society must have come from somewhere.
 Conceivably, it might have arisen on some
alien planet never having known the State and
discovering the non-aggression principle early. One
can have some obvious drama when this innocent
society runs into their first statists—such as Terrans!&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;But if it arose from our present society, then the
people must have developed libertarian behavior
modes. Note I did not say libertarian theories. In order
for a libertarian society to have developed, the
libertarians in thought must have become libertarians
in deed. This has nothing to do with signing up,
voting, or declarations.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;A society becomes libertarian when the populace
refuses, en masse, to obey the State, to submit under
threat, to pay taxes, to use State currency, or to accept
handouts and subsidies. This self—sufficiency will be
maintained as long as the society is, and this will be
reflected in all customs, transactions, traditions and
even the romances of the libertarians.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Thus behavior patterns at variance with an individual
 self-governance—of children, of parents, even of
the “handicapped"—will be tolerated and could be
found—but they would be clearly noted as aberrations.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;h3&gt;Alien Libertarian Societies&lt;/h3&gt;
&lt;p&gt;The construction of libertarian alien societies has
been about as common (or uncommon) as those of
Terran human ones. Asimov had an anarchist society
in &lt;em&gt;The Gods Themselves&lt;/em&gt; (though I surprised him in an
elevator by pointing it out to him); Anderson in &lt;em&gt;Winter
of the World&lt;/em&gt; (although the aliens were ex-human
mutants). Many others mention alien societies in
passing but “forget” to give them a government or
politics.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Libertarianism is based on individual intelligence
(free will) and its interaction with matter (property).
Hence any beings with the smarts and material
possessions can have a libertarian society. Whether or
not they will be more or less likely to than humans are
is the subject for a nice long letter or mailing comment
debate. For starters, Anderson thought that mutants
were more capable than humans to “handle anarchy”
&lt;em&gt;(op. cit.).&lt;/em&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Since Ursula LeGuin has both functioning human
anarchies and alien societies in her Ekumen, it will be
interesting to see what she does with the interactions.
Other well-known authors currently of libertarian
leanings whose future works should be observed for
anarchies are Heinlein, Van Vogt, Bester, Wilson
(both), Moorcock and maybe even Richard E. Geis.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Pros you would &lt;em&gt;not&lt;/em&gt; expect an anarchy from (except
inadvertently) are Niven and Pournelle, Asimov,
Herbert, and Reynolds. I don’t know what to expect of
RA. Lafferty.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;CONCLUDING DETAILS&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;There are a lot of technical questions one might
want to follow up if building a libertarian society in
close detail. There is simply no room to delve into all
the possibilities. For example, how would a libertarian
society fight a state that appeared suddenly? What
kind of heavy philosophical debates would members
of the libertarian society get hung up on? How could
garbage be collected and murder mysteries solved?
The answers to all these is that it depends on the
context you have developed.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;For those of you wanting expert consulting on
libertarian technicalities, contact me at NLE. This
article was written simply to prevent the most obvious
errors and inadvertent smears (all smears of libertarianism
 will henceforth be assumed advertent!). You
may now start writing; class dismissed.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;hr /&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Clear Ether!&lt;br /&gt;
Volume 4, Number 2 / March 1979&lt;br /&gt;
Pages 1, 4&lt;/p&gt;</summary></entry></feed>