<?xml version="1.0" encoding="utf-8"?>
<feed xmlns="http://www.w3.org/2005/Atom"><title>Collected writings of Samuel Edward Konkin III</title><link href="http://www.sek3.net/" rel="alternate"></link><link href="http://www.sek3.net/feeds/libertarian-review.atom.xml" rel="self"></link><id>http://www.sek3.net/</id><updated>2015-05-10T00:00:00+08:00</updated><entry><title>Invaders from the State</title><link href="http://www.sek3.net/invaders-from-the-state.html" rel="alternate"></link><published>2015-05-10T00:00:00+08:00</published><updated>2015-05-10T00:00:00+08:00</updated><author><name>Samuel Edward Konkin III</name></author><id>tag:www.sek3.net,1976-03-01:invaders-from-the-state.html</id><summary type="html">&lt;p&gt;The Libertarian Party: Cause for Hope or Trojan Horse?&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Three Views: Toole, Samuel Edward Konkin III, and Edward H. Crane III&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;h2&gt;Invaders from the State&lt;/h2&gt;
&lt;h4&gt;By Samuel Edward Konkin III&lt;/h4&gt;
&lt;p&gt;The Libertarian Party is the vehicle of an invasion
from the State into the ranks of the libertarian movement.
 Its defenders, true to the State’s need for mysticism
 and contradiction, cry the LP is the practical
strategy for obtaining the free society; failing that, it
is another tactic, to be tried and tested with other
tactics; failing that, it is an educational tool, to lure
converts as a step to hardcore counter-economic activism.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;The LP is None of the Above. It is a vicious instrument
 of the State. For libertarians, it is immoral, impractical,
 uneconomic, strategically unsound, and
praxeologically debilitating.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;The foundation of statism is deliberate mysticism,
calculated to gain the acquiescence of the oppressed
or “the sanction of the victim.” In order, to obtain
this “authority,” or legitimization of immoral actions,
 it creates meaningless forms to bedazzle the
masses—big juju! Such was the divine rule of kings,
such was nationalism, such were the emperors and
czars restoring the dead glory of Rome. Such, too,is
the game of democracy. The rule is to withhold violence
 but jockey for the use of acceptable, legitimized
violence. Those who disputed over the reins of power
were called, in Hanoverian England, parties to the
dispute.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;A political party, then, is a collective whose overriding
 purpose and reason for being is to seize control
of the State for plunder and coercion for its cause.
(Restraint of short-term plunder—liberalism—is one
possibility.) All claims to the contrary are buncombe
and cant.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;A “Libertarian Party” is a pure contradiction—if
&lt;em&gt;libertarian&lt;/em&gt; means anticoercion and thus anti-State.
Those who openly join it proclaim their allegiance to
a “secret gang of murderers and thieves”—dropping
the secrecy. And so proclaim themselves immoral.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Most North Americans have an inarticulate understanding
 that politics is a nauseating power grab. Five
out of every eight eligible rejected their vote in 1974,
preferring not to soil themselves in the game. These
people respond positively to an image of libertarianism
 as a vehicle to a Society Without Politics, and
they get confused by and hostile to urgings to register
and vote for a position that believes in neither registration
 nor voting.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Moreover, many voters are browbeaten and intimidated
 into voting by State-enforced propaganda laying
 unwarranted guilt trips on the reluctant voter.
The same pleas as justify conscription are heard:
“Duty! Honor! Country! Save Democracy!” An attack
 upon this cant relieves such people and causes
them to look favorably on the movement not requiring
 such petty self-sacrifice.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;The LP turns away the vast majority hungering for
a consistent libertarian position. It is thus an exceedingly
 potent, practical weapon—for the State!&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Hundreds of thousands of dollars are wasted by
libertarians who donate time and treasure to the
bloated coffers of the LP. Not even Nelson Rockefeller
 could afford the lavish $6.50 per vote squandered
by the Tuccille for Governor Campaign of New
York’s Free Libertarian Party in 1974. And Rockefeller
 hires &lt;em&gt;his&lt;/em&gt; campaign workers.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;As a shining example of market efficiency, the Libertarian
 Party is a great argument for bureaucracy.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;The last stand of LP defenders is to claim that at
least politicians can use the party as a stepping stone
outward. But in fact, the LP obtains such people only
as they see the party approaching power. The professional
 Machiavellians do not care to whom their allegiance
 is due, only who can pay off.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Nearly all the ranks of the LP are made up of idealists
 unaware of alternative activist opportunities, and
the vast majority of new converts would not vote if
the LP did not snow them into it. The turnover is
large (nearly 50 percent a year in New York, for
example) and most of the ex-members “Browne-Out,”
 rejecting politics and often more fruitful forms
of activism.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Thus the LP either remystifies the statist process or
neutralizes the State’s opponents. Again, a most winning
 strategy—for the State.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Recent researches reviewed in &lt;em&gt;Laissez Faire Review,&lt;/em&gt;
&lt;em&gt;Libertarian Forum,&lt;/em&gt; and &lt;em&gt;Libertarian Review&lt;/em&gt; have
pointed out the psychological necessity of conditioning
 submissive responses to authority as a prerequisite
to power holding sway. The LP teaches the “libertarian”
 to submit his will to the collective and execute
decisions he opposes for the “will of the majority”
and the “good of the party.” Parliamentary procedure
 teaches him frustration, wheel-spinning, and
abandonment of market-organization. Backroom
deals, backstabbing, and power blocs teach him survival—in
 a State. None of the party activities are calculated
 to reward initiative, individualism, or risk for
profit. And the LP needs a monopoly, for if it is to
win—the overriding necessity—it cannot tolerate a
split. Thus is collectivism reborn.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;And thus, when all is summed, would the State remain
 triumphant should the party thrive. Already the
LP discards its idealists for the Machiavellian backs
in its leadership, in preparation for its role. The
Libertarian Party stands five-fold condemned as an
invader from the State, a Trojan Horse, a Saruman,
a Judas.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Until we free ourselves, we cannot preach the freeing
 of others without rightfully gaining their mocking
laughter.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;The Libertarian Party must go—now!&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;hr /&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Samuel Edward Konkin III is creator and editor of
New Libertarian weekly. He has been an active member
of four political parties—including the LP—in Canada
and the United States.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;hr /&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Libertarian Review&lt;br /&gt;
Volume 5 Number 2 / March-April 1976&lt;br /&gt;
Pages 10-11&lt;/p&gt;</summary></entry></feed>