<?xml version="1.0" encoding="utf-8"?>
<feed xmlns="http://www.w3.org/2005/Atom"><title>Collected writings of Samuel Edward Konkin III</title><link href="http://www.sek3.net/" rel="alternate"></link><link href="http://www.sek3.net/feeds/libertarian-forum.atom.xml" rel="self"></link><id>http://www.sek3.net/</id><updated>2015-05-19T00:00:00+08:00</updated><entry><title>Canadian Separatism: the Second Front</title><link href="http://www.sek3.net/canadian-separatism-the-second-front.html" rel="alternate"></link><published>2015-05-19T00:00:00+08:00</published><updated>2015-05-19T00:00:00+08:00</updated><author><name>Samuel Edward Konkin III</name></author><id>tag:www.sek3.net,1980-03-01:canadian-separatism-the-second-front.html</id><summary type="html">&lt;h2&gt;Canadian Separatism: the Second Front&lt;/h2&gt;
&lt;h4&gt;by Samuel E. Konkin II&lt;/h4&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Even the most anti-political libertarian has to admit elections do
change things, even if only because they are believed and acted
upon. The most striking example in the democratic enclave of
Western society may well be the two Canadian federal elections
within the past year. And the most recent results could well portend
strong gains for objective libertarianism, grist for the activist’s mill.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;After 16 long years of Liberal (pro-U.S. centrist party, like unto
U.S. Democrats with right and left wings) Party rule, eleven of them
under the Gallic Kennedy-type, Pierre Eliot Trudeau, the West,
Maritimes, and English-speaking East-Central of Canada voted for
Alberta’s Joe Clark and his Progressive Conservative (mildly anti-U.S.,
 centre-right Party, like unto mix of British Tories and French
Gaullists with a smattering of American Liberal Republicanism)
Party. Since Quebec stubbornly supported Trudeau’s Liberals and
the Social Credit (pro-U.S., radical right party, similar to a mixture
of Birchers and populists), Clark could only muster a minority
government, though only four seats short of a majority. The
Creditistes had five seats, well, six originally until one was bought
out by the Tories (as the P.C.’s are known, the Liberals are called
“Grits”), and the assumption by most pundits in the Canadian
press was that fiery Fabien Roy and his Creditistes would prop up
their ideological near-kinsmen.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Such was not to be. Although Trudeau was berated for his
arrogance, it was nothing compared to that displayed by Clark &amp;amp;
Co. to the Social Credit Party.[1] After dragging out the calling of
Parliament after the election to a record four months, Clark
presented a budget calling for higher taxes and more controls and
assumed the free-enterprise Creditistes had nowhere else to go and
support him. In the greatest act of political moral suicide since
Gilles Gregoire blocked the House of Commons single-handedly to
begin Social-Credit Separatism and paralyse the federal
government, the Creditistes refused to vote for the budget. The
Liberals, smelling blood, swam back from their scattered
constituencies, parties (cocktail variety), and homes to join the
social-democrat New Democrat Party (NDP) into narrowly
defeating the budget. In any heir of British Parliamentary tradition,
that constitutes the strongest possible vote of non-confidence, and
Clark promptly resigned, calling for an election.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;The winter election, coming just eight months after the last one,
was manifestly unpopular, and Clark’s 18-cent gas tax even less so.
The Liberals regained seats in the Maritimes and Ontario, and
wiped out the Creditistes in Quebec (so much for the rewards of
morality in the political arena); the NDP further cut into the Tories
in the West. Worst of all, from a libertarian political viewpoint,
Trudeau won an absolute majority of seats and remains safe from
non-confidence motions (and elections) for the full five-year
maximum term. Ironically, Trudeau was about to step down in
disgrace when the election suddenly happened, and the Liberals
had been gearing up for the bruising leadership convention.
&lt;em&gt;Maclean’s&lt;/em&gt; (the Time-Newsweek of Canada) called his return on the
cover of its election issue: “The Second Coming.”&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;From a Fabian political libertarian viewpoint, the February 1980
(“Valentine’s Day”) election could be considered a gain for statism,
with the loss of the proto-libertarian Creditistes and a majority
government. Furthermore, Trudeau is the champion of strong,
central government, and will be using his prime ministry to battle
Rene Levesque’s Parti Quebec (commonly called pequistes) in the
coming referendum on “Quebec sovereignty.” This concept, by the
way, requires some twisted unraveling, thanks to Leveque’s
continued weaseling and selling out of Separatism, but it basically
allows the voters of Quebec to vote for “separatism” without
actually getting it; it’s taken as a bargaining ploy by most of the
media pundits to give Levesque a stronger hand in bargaining with
Trudeau for Provincial &lt;em&gt;vs&lt;/em&gt; federal rights and powers.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Before dealing with this crucial libertarian issue of separatism, or
as the Yanks (especially the Yankees from Mississippi) like to call
the concept, secession, there was one direct blow for libertarianism
in the election. No, the very conservative Canadian Libertarian
Party (overwhelmingly minarchist, anti-communist in foreign
policy, and worst of all, anti-separatist because the strongest
faction in the PQ is socialist-liberal) got not only zero seats, but
failed to get any significant mention in the press. At least the CBC
election coverage mentioned only the four parties above and
“Others:” &lt;em&gt;Maclean’s&lt;/em&gt; also made no mention of the CLP before,
during or after the election. Ah, but the Rhinoceros Party, a
Canadian variant of the “Nobody for President” campaign,
received mention on the CBC (Canadian Broadcasting
Corporation, government-owned and largest TV network) and
fully a third-page in Maclean’s. More importantly, quoting from
&lt;em&gt;Maclean’s,&lt;/em&gt; “While all other parties watched their slim Quebec
footholds trampled under the Liberal thumping, the Rhinocerotics
saw their total vote almost double to 110,000. “But we weren’t
worried,” confides Rhino heavy Charles McKenzie. ‘We took the
precaution of doubling our number of candidates.’ One bitter
Quebec Tory candidate, Clark aide Andre Payette, appearing on
the provincially owned TV network, Radio-Quebec, after its
election centre had been invaded by a Rhino band, confessed to
having a lot in common with Rhino star Sonia (Tickle) Cote—such
as roughly the same number of votes. Sonia, perched beside him in
her clown outfit and hanging over her accordion, could only look
up and blush coyly from under her single forehorn.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;“Meanwhile, back at their east-end Montreal rent-a-hall, the Rhino
machine—basically a hippi revival, complete with
construction boots, giggling kids and barking dogs—danced
drunkenly around a giant TV screen, celebrating the 1,000-plus
votes won by a horned cousin in Calgary.”&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Calgary, brings us to the point of this article. The second largest
and second most conservative city in Alberta (and the most
Americanized, with its own John Birch Society chapter) after
Edmonton, the capital, is probably the most libertarian in the sense
most Americans would think of it, with a thriving anti-tax
movement winning plebiscites just like Howard Jarvis. All Alberta,
like British Columbia and Saskatchewan on either side, voted in
zero Liberals, and while BC and Saskatchewan voted in many
NDPs, Alberta went solidly PC, showing those Eastern bandits
what it thought of those who would steal its precious oil. Calgary
also is the home of provincial premier Peter Lougheed, himself a
Kennedy-esque type who ousted the Alberta Social Credit Party in
1972 and remained in power since. Lougheed has bloated the
Alberta Heritage Fund with oil royalties to the point where he
could probably buy the entire Canadian army should it ever be
used to invade a seceding Alberta. Would ultra-right, tax-free,
regulation-loose, anti-union Alberta secede? Undoubtedly the most
bigoted anti-frog (French equivalent of “nigger”) area in Canada,
would Alberta go separatist? &lt;em&gt;Maclean’s&lt;/em&gt; seems to think so.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Back when this author was the firebrand Social Credit leader at
the University of Alberta (1964-1968), he had to look long and hard
for another secessionist, even those who liked the idea but not the
French Canadians. Then a report about five years ago mentioned
that an Alberta separatist party had been started and 500 members
had joined. &lt;em&gt;Maclean’s&lt;/em&gt; reported, in the issue after its election
special, “For Albertans, it was back to the barricades, back to their
traditional sense of grievance and isolation. Having felt themselves
a part of the federal government for the first time since John
Diefenbaker’s days, the shock of being on the outside looking east
again have shoved some toward separatism. At the Canada West
Foundation, the think tank devoted to forging a new Canada
within Confederation, the telephone was ringing at 8:15 the
morning after. ‘I picked it up and someone said, “I feel totally
disenfranchised today,” ’ says administration officer Nancy
Sanford. ‘Every five minutes since, there has been another call. A
quarter of the callers are looking for a separatist party, which we
aren’t. The rest are saying they feel totally sick and they want to
voice their frustration to someone.”&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;How serious is this possibility of Alberta separatism taken? Of
course, short of shipping oil by pipeline to Montana, land-locked
Alberta has the Pacific coastline—and an equally strong separatist
pull. Again, from &lt;em&gt;Maclean’s,&lt;/em&gt; “BC IN POLITICAL ISOLATION.
And it is Perrault ((Liberal senator from BC)) who is reminding
Trudeau of events such as last week’s radio survey that showed six
out of every 10 callers in favor of separation from the rest of
Canada. ‘But usually it’s just the dissidents who call these shows,’
he philosophizes.”&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;The quote comes from the lead article in Maclean’s, along with a
cartoon showing Trudeau facing a battery of microphones, with an
array of knives, arrows, tomahawks and darts protruding from his
backside “. . . and I am reminded that while we face the
threat of separatism in Quebec, we must not turn our backs on the
alienation of the West . . .” Yes, the threat of Western separatism is
taken seriously.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Even though the other two Western Provinces elected only two
Liberals total (from urban Manitoba) giving an Alberta—British
Columbia “Rocky Mountain Republic” a nice buffer zone, the
battle will be fought economically, not on the battlefield. The fact
that Alberta is rich and economically free, and the rest of Canada is
suffering under austerity budgets and heavy government regulation
and taxation is the key. And it’s also the problem because there is
no firm ideological leadership in the West. Lougheed is simply a
conservative who is following the political dynamics of the
situation which leads him to the coming confrontation with
Ottawa (the federal capital) over oil controls. But he’s not fighting
for Alberta non-regulation of petroleum vs federal regulation,
rather they’re arguing how the plunder should be divided. This
could kill any principled rally against the central state..&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;And, finally, the link between Quebec and Western separatists
must be established. Again, Lougheed is not the medium, a symbol
of a (relatively sophisticated, to be sure) anti-frog mentality, and
not likely to win Levesque’s support. The old Social Credit Party,
strong precisely in Alberta, Quebec (and still the provincial
government in British Columbia) would have been the perfect
vehicle—but it’s at a new low in strength, most of its old
supporters supporting the pequistes in Quebec and the PCs in
Alberta.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;The potential for libertarian organization is obvious.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;hr /&gt;
&lt;p&gt;[1] Apologies for name-dropping, but Prime Minister Clark was a
PM at the University of Alberta when this writer, in his pre-libertarian
days, sat as Social Credit whip in model parliament and
remembered his arrogance well toward the SC Party, then the
dominant one in Alberta politics.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;hr /&gt;
&lt;p&gt;The Libertarian Forum&lt;br /&gt;
Volume 13 Number 2 / March-April 1980&lt;br /&gt;
Pages 7-8&lt;/p&gt;</summary><category term="Canada"></category><category term="separatism"></category></entry><entry><title>The Other North American Election</title><link href="http://www.sek3.net/the-other-north-american-election.html" rel="alternate"></link><published>2015-05-19T00:00:00+08:00</published><updated>2015-05-19T00:00:00+08:00</updated><author><name>Samuel Edward Konkin III</name></author><id>tag:www.sek3.net,1973-01-01:the-other-north-american-election.html</id><summary type="html">&lt;h2&gt;The Other North American Election&lt;/h2&gt;
&lt;h4&gt;By Samuel Edward Konkin III&lt;/h4&gt;
&lt;p&gt;While Richard Nixon bored everyone with his landslide on November 7,
Canadians were treated to a cliff-hanger a week earlier on October 30.
The pollsters confidently predicted a Trudeau return as Maritime
provinces’ results swung slightly towards the Liberal Party, and Quebec
cut the Progressive Conservative seats from four to two (out of 74). True,
the Social Credit Rally (Ralliement Creditiste) increased their popular
vote substantially, but gained only one seat. Then Ontario came in with
the social democratic New Democrat Party and the Progressive Conservatives
 slashing into the Grit (Liberal) standings. And then the West.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;In Alberta, all four Liberal seats were buried under a Tory (PC)
avalanche. British Columbia moved the Tories even with the Grits, and
brought in the NDP main strength. The Northwest Territories gave the
NDP their first “frontier” seat (Grit loss) and the Tories held on to the
Yukon to put them one seat up, 109-108.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Canada does not allow absentee balloting, except for one special case.
The Social Credit Party’s sole gain was at the expense of Jean-Luc Pepin,
a Liberal Cabinet Minister involved in what Murray Rothbard called
Quebec’s “White Terror” suspension of civil rights of a few years ago,
and, since the Creditistes are the federal party which most free market
libertarians (especially minarchists) in the U.S. would sympathize with,
it seemed like divine justice. Unfortunately, the military votes Grit, and
their absentee ballots reversed the 100-vote margin, knocking the
Creditistes back to 14 seats. Libertarians can probably read symbolism
into that as well.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;The final standings of 109 seats each for the Liberals and P. C.’s, 30 for
the NDP, 14 for SC, one Independent Conservative and one Independent
(speaker of the House Lucien Lamoureux—non-partisan) tell the
average American nothing, assuming he even heard of them. For the
libertarians wanting of know who to cheer and who to boo—as Dr.
Rothbard is wont—even less. I shall undertake here to give you a
programme to go with your scorecard.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;The Social Credit Party used to be based in the rightist West, Alberta
and British Columbia, and was a free market, pro-American party with a
funny money policy they could not legislate because they had only controlled
 provincial governments. They never had more than a minority in
the national House of Commons. In 1963, they defeated John Diefen-baker’s
 minority Tory government because he failed to balance the
budget. In 1962, Real Caouette led his Quebecers into the House in larger
numbers than the Western wing, and the party eventually split. The
Western wing withdrew in favor of P. C.’s to stem the Trudeau sweep of
1968, and never recovered. Caouette kept his more orthodix Social Credit
position, appealing populistically to the Quebec habitants (peasant
farmers) and stayed in the House. Recently he tried to expand westward,
but failed to restore the party outside Quebec (although there are still a
few Socred diehards lurking in rightist circles in ranch and oil country).
The Alberta provincial Socreds were thrown out of office for the first
time in 35 years in 1970 by Kennedyesque Tory Peter Lougheed, and their
very survival as a party depends on Lougheed’s self-destruction. This 
year in British Columbia, W. A. C. Bennett’s 20-year Socred regime was
ousted by the NDP in an even greater victory, marking a swing from far
Right to far Left in the Canadian four-party spectrum. Although Caouette
increased his popular vote markedly, and signs of organization were seen
again throughout Canada, the recent net effect for the “good guys” (least
worst guys) is down.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;The Leftist bad guys, the New Democrat Party, which is labour backed
and oriented, like the British Labour Party, now has three provincial
governments (B. C, Saskatchewan, and Manitoba) and their largest
number of seats ever in the Federal House. American investors are fleeing
 B. C. right now, and Canadian capitalists are screaming to the federal
government to bail them out by preventing nationalization of federal
regulated industries. &lt;em&gt;Plus ça change, plus c’est la même chose.&lt;/em&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;The big gains federally were reaped by Robert Stanfield’s Progressive
Conservative Party, but it cannot take over the government without 25
more seats—and the Creditistes haven’t got that many. The Tories are
conservative, but in the British/European sense, not (except for a small
Ontario faction) in the American quasi-libertarian sense. Hence they love
mercantilism and fear gradual socialism much less. Thus NDP support
for the right Welfarist concessions is thinkable, and the NDP’s and PC’s
both are anti-American (just as the Liberals and SC’s are pro-American).
Their foreign policy might seem more appealing to a libertarian; but it
manifests itself in increasing government regulation of corporations
(50% of Canadian companies are American controlled) and in little which
could be considered objective anti-imperialism. The NDP leader, David
Lewis, will “throw his support behind whichever of the old line parties is
prepared to deal adequately with unemployment, inflation, old age pensions,
 and a more equitable tax system.”[1] Coming from a socialist, that seems
ominous. I doubt that libertarians could imagine a worse nightmare
 than a de facto socialist-traditionalist coalition.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Trudeaumania is gone, but Pierre Elliot Trudeau clings on. He has not
resigned, and it looks as if he will try to keep governing, daring the Opposition
 to precipitate an election by defeating him on a non-confidence
motion. Here, precedent is murky. There is no reason the figurehead
Governor-General can’t ask the Tories to try to gain confidence for a
majority—but in 1926, Governor General Lord Byng refused Liberal
Mackenzie King’s request for dissolution of Parliament, and invited
Conservative Arthur Meighen to govern. His bungling Progressive supporters
 blew a “pairing”, bringing him down only days later, and William
Lyon Mackenzie King rode to victory attacking Byng’s interference.
Would Roland Michener have the guts of Lord Byng? Ultimately, the
Tories may be thwarted by this vestige of royal privilege. Michener was a
Conservative, to add to the irony, but was appointed by a Liberal government,
 following a recent cross-party tradition.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Still, Trudeau has a problem if Michener doesn’t give him an issue. The
electorate might decide to finish the job by giving Stanfield a majority.
Diefenbaker ended 22 years of Liberal government in 1957, and dissolved
his minority government early in 1958 calling for just such a majority. He
won a record 208 out of 265 seats.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;On the other hand, Lester Bowles Pearson won two minority
governments in a row of 1963 and 1965 after a Tory minority of 1962, failing
 to get the majority he craved. He limped along in the Centre, depending
 on Social Credit support.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;It is in the Grits’ interest to give the Tories the government, so that
Stanfield can begin to alienate voters. But it’s not in Trudeau’s interest,
as shown by Diefenbaker’s ouster after his election defeat by a particularly
 brutal purge which caused enough resentment in the West to
give Trudeau his 1968 victory in the first place. Trudeau’s ouster would
not be so regionally oriented, because half of the Liberal seats are in
Quebec anyway, and his followers have nowhere to go but the Creditistes,
the Tories being unthinkable and the NDP frowned on by the Catholic
Church.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;The French-English split is being played up by foreign papers, and the
Separatists may be bolstered by the defeat of their centralist enemy
Trudeau—but that is a Provincial effect, not a Federal one. Furthermore,
 resentment against compulsory bilingualism/biculturalism is
found in the third of the population of non-WASP origin (mostly in the
West) such as German, Ukrainian, Galician, Icelander, Dutch, Russian,
and others who are just speaking English in the first or second generation.
 The only real amelioration will be found in reviving the Social Credit
and Union Nationale’s (a Quebec provincial party, recently defeated by
the Grits) demand for greater decentralism and provincial rights. The
present trend is the other way, but Canadians are a remarkably non-revolutionary
 lot, pointing with pride to their “evolution” from Great
Britain, as opposed to the Americans’ messy violence. Quebec independence
 will be gained gradually if at all, by the Parti Quebec
parliamentarily (with both RIN-socialistic-and RN-Creditiste-wings) and
not by the ten to fifteen FLQ[2] goons.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Revolution in Canada is a bigger joke than in the U.S., and rather than
radical change, resulting from elimination of Trudeau’s flashy, slightly-leftist
 liberalism (he flirted with price controls but never implemented
them, by the way) one should expect stodginess, anti-communist witch-hunts
 from Liberal renegade Paul Hellyer, and the ominous economic
changes resulting from NDP support. Canadian libertarians and their
American allies should be hoping for a new election and a minority
government with Creditiste swing vote power. Failing that, how about
Parliamentary Chaos?&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;hr /&gt;
&lt;p&gt;[1] Page 1, &lt;em&gt;The Edmonton Journal,&lt;/em&gt; Tuesday, October 31, 1972.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;[2] Front de Liberation Quebecois RIN = Reassemblement pour l’Independence Nationale, and RN = Ralliement Nationale. The &lt;em&gt;Nationale&lt;/em&gt; recurring in Quebec party names has the opposite meaning of “nationwide”.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;hr /&gt;
&lt;p&gt;SPECIAL NOTE ABOUT THE AUTHOR: Before becoming a well-known libertarian activist and writer, Mr. Konkin was a Socred activist, and Chairman of the University of Alberta Social Credit Party from 1966-68. He became senior participant in the Model Parliaments, and was involved in all Canadian and Alberta elections from 1962 to 1968. He is now a foreign student at New York University, a candidate for a Ph. D. in Theoretical Chemistry.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;hr /&gt;
&lt;p&gt;The Libertarian Forum&lt;br /&gt;
Volume 4 Number 11 / January 1973&lt;br /&gt;
Pages 4, 6&lt;/p&gt;</summary><category term="Canada"></category><category term="politics"></category><category term="election"></category></entry></feed>