<?xml version="1.0" encoding="utf-8"?>
<feed xmlns="http://www.w3.org/2005/Atom"><title>Collected writings of Samuel Edward Konkin III</title><link href="https://www.sek3.net/" rel="alternate"></link><link href="https://www.sek3.net/feeds/southern-libertarian-messenger.atom.xml" rel="self"></link><id>https://www.sek3.net/</id><updated>2015-07-12T00:00:00+08:00</updated><entry><title>To the Editor</title><link href="https://www.sek3.net/to-the-editor.html" rel="alternate"></link><published>2015-05-10T00:00:00+08:00</published><updated>2015-05-10T00:00:00+08:00</updated><author><name>Samuel Edward Konkin III</name></author><id>tag:www.sek3.net,1973-03-01:to-the-editor.html</id><summary type="html">&lt;h2&gt;To the Editor&lt;/h2&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Editor:&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;I would like to forward to your readers some information I have concerning the
organizations you mention in your TAX RESISTANCE issue of the &lt;em&gt;Southern Libertarian
Messenger,&lt;/em&gt; also known as the February, 1973 issue, alias Vol. I, No. 10. A fine
publication, by the way, worthy of the Libertarian Regional Press.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Andy Thornton, the current National Office of SLAM, is working at the Laissez
Faire Book Store because he was purged from War Tax Resisters for agorist deviationism.
 I do not believe in that crap about withdrawing sanction from every business
 which happens to be run by immoral people, i.e., those with differing political-ethical
 views, but I would think it appropriate that any libertarians dealing
with WTR indicate in their communications their agorist persuasion and take any
opportunity possible for berating WTR for their left bias.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Not all your readers are old Rightists, like us, David. (Maybe I Just speak
for myself?) You should explain to them when mentioning &lt;em&gt;The American Mercury&lt;/em&gt; that
it is the flagship publication of Willis Carto’s Fraudulent Empire of Hate. Carto
is a Yockeyist, the author of the &lt;em&gt;Introduction to Imperium.&lt;/em&gt; However, even the Nazis
 are abandoning him because of the fact that he runs his &lt;em&gt;American Mercury/Washington
 Observer&lt;/em&gt;-etc. as a shill, constantly soliciting funds from the aspiring-intellectual
 bigots for actions and projects which either never take off or are far
below expectations. I was highly amused by that large ad the &lt;em&gt;New Banner&lt;/em&gt; gave the
&lt;em&gt;Mercury.&lt;/em&gt; Those ex-objectivists never did get to know the Right, and they are paying
 for their Rand-imposed ignorance.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;You also might mention that the Student Libertarian Action Movement and the
Free Libertarian Party radical caucus, with hoped-for assists from the New York
Libertarian Association and the Society for Individual Liberty, will be in Libertarian
 Alliance for the Demonstration TAX IS THEFT, April 14 at 10AM, at 120
Church Street, Manhattan (the IRS Centre). Any freedom-symps among your readers
who happen to be around then, and want to get into Libertarian Action, are welcome.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Don’t forget to smash the state. You forgot yesterday, and, sure enough,
it’s still here.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;—Samuel Edward Konkin&lt;br /&gt;
New York, NY&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;em&gt;The Editor Replies:&lt;/em&gt;
Thanks for setting-us straight, Sam. Some additional information has come
to light since we went to press last month. The Tax Rebellion Committee (1843
E. Balmont, Fresno, CA 93701) distributes some material on resisting and abolishing
 the income tax, and Henry Hohenstein (Suite 3K, 2530 (Continued on page 6)
[Hasn’t been scanned any further]&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;hr /&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Southern Libertarian Messenger&lt;br /&gt;
Editor: David Rosinger&lt;br /&gt;
March, 1973 / Vol. I, No. 11&lt;br /&gt;
Page 5&lt;/p&gt;</summary><category term="taxes"></category><category term="demos"></category><category term="SLAM"></category></entry><entry><title>Know Thine Enemy!</title><link href="https://www.sek3.net/know-thine-enemy.html" rel="alternate"></link><published>2015-05-10T00:00:00+08:00</published><updated>2015-05-10T00:00:00+08:00</updated><author><name>Samuel Edward Konkin III</name></author><id>tag:www.sek3.net,1973-01-01:know-thine-enemy.html</id><summary type="html">&lt;h2&gt;Know Thine Enemy!&lt;/h2&gt;
&lt;h3&gt;1941—1973&lt;/h3&gt;
&lt;h4&gt;by Samuel Edward Konkin III&lt;/h4&gt;
&lt;blockquote&gt;
&lt;p&gt;I have read both Higher
 Circles[1] land Conspiracy[2]
 but fail to see
how talking about
“THEM” advances libertarian
 thinking.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;—David F. Nolan, postscript
 to last of the
Nolan-Konkin Letters
(NLN 15).&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/blockquote&gt;
&lt;p&gt;The year is 1941, and
you are there. You have
sat at the knee of Albert
J. Nock, perhaps along with Frank Chodorov.
 You dig through old bookstores to
find books by Lysander Spooner and
trade copies of Benjamin Tucker’s &lt;em&gt;Liberty&lt;/em&gt;
 with the “Remnant” like yourself.
You speak out, perhaps on a campus,
against “that man in the White House,”
and his eclectic but statist economics.
You are a libertarian activist, perhaps
ahead of your time. And there is a
bloody holocaust in Europe.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Many of the people you associate
with on the Right, represented by Eugene
 Lyons’ &lt;em&gt;American Mercury,&lt;/em&gt; are for
going to war against National Socialism
and Fascism, extreme Leftist ideologues
viciously out to uproot and radicalize
anything remotely “conservative.” According
 to the information available at
the time[3] they intend to ravage Europe
like a horde of Huns, with fire and
sword, blood and iron. Next to them,
the Bolsheviks seem safe, tame, and non-interventionist.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;The Left is almost universally opposed
 to American participation, at
least until June; then the bellicose,
more-American-than-thou Communists
“Wrap themselves in the American Flag
so you can hardly see the hammer-and-sickle”
 and join the crusade against
their erstwhile ally, and split with
the predominately pacifist Socialists.[4]
The ideologues and purveyors of political
 nostrums scream for “War!”, to save
the Jews, the French, the Russians, Europe,
 Asia. . . the World! And you?&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Even with this background,
 you may be ready to go
along. After all, nothing is
more statist than Fascism,
right? Would it not be worth
it to use limited states (such
as the U.S. and Great Britain)
against the totalitarians?&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;This fork in the road towards
 either successful anti-state
 strategy or towards becoming
 dupes of the power
elite creates a choice which
requires additional information
to rationally make. Suppose, unlike many
of your friends and allies, you have been
talking to the Harry Elmer Barneses, the
Charles Beards, and their students—talking
 about THEM: the ruling class, power
elite, superstatists, etc. You know from
Franz Oppenheimer (through Nock) that the
State splits society into two classes:
those that make a net gain by its existence
 (the “exploiters”) and those that
lose (the “exploited”) and leading those
whose wealth is amassed by wholesale theft
and murder, the elite plutocrats who the
Revisionists expose. You know how they
caused World War I, and the financial killings
 (non-market, needless to say) the
Warburgs, Mellons, and Shiffs made. You
look for signs of that around you.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;And if you look deep enough, they are
there. Speeches of “Liberal” bureaucrats
exhorting support for the newly enacted
draft and the mobilizing War Machine.[6]
Plans in the “in” Journals for heavy economic
 controls, cartelization, and nationalization
 as in World War I—but these
won’t be dismantled this time.[7] You see
Roosevelt meeting with Churchill, promising
 him all support “short of war,”
and then see his actions: U.S. Navy ships
firing on Axis submarines, U.S. “gift” of
50 destroyers to the U.K., U.S. invasion
of Iceland, U.S. support to China in the
Far East, U.S. embargo of Japan, U.S.
seizure of all Japanese assets in the U.S.,
U.S. refusal to negotiate with an almost
begging Japan unless Japan denounces all
her allies,
abandons all territories outside its own islands, and completely reverses her foreign
 policy to subservience under the U.S.[8]&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;With an ounce of morality in you, you Join America First! You campaign
against Roosevelt’s actions, and expose him at [FIXME: missed text?] every turn. You
burn your fellow libertarians’ ears with your Revisionism so they won’t support
the domestic power grab, and tell everyone to fight the fascism at home, leaving
Europe to fight its own. You may fail when the Japanese are driven to bomb
Pearl Harbor to get “them” before “they” get the Japanese, causing the American
populace to drop their isolationism and follow Roosevelt. And the Germans fall
into the trap by almost insanely living up to their Pact with Japan, even though
their hands are full in Africa and Russia. But thirty years later, a new, resurgent
 libertarian movement arises out of the Right and Left where your allies
had become dupes, denouncing them for their folly, and looking back for trades of
your heroic opposition for their new inspiration.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Today, the “Peace” movement rolls over, fetches, and does-simple tricks for
Richard Nixon when it comes to his foreign policy. An era of detente, thawing of
the Cold War, peace everywhere, myths shattering, and the Wall Street Barons realizing
 the limitations of U.S. “world policeman” role. What shivers of ecstacy!&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;What a pile ordure to any Revisionist with his nose open! China, manipulated
 into a paranoia of Russians, reversing policy to desiring U.S. presence in
Asia as a “counter-balance”! The Union of Soviet Socialist Republics, finally
paying the price of following Marxist zero-think on agricultural economics and
starving, goes hat in hand to the U.S., begging for food. The terms are $24 million
 a year, to pay a debt (until 2001) neither the Russian slaves nor even their
present masters incurred thirty years before, to repay not the individuals residing
 in North America who had originally been ripped-off for 100-times as much,
but those who follow in the footsteps of the thieves. In short, every Russian is
paying a dime a year tribute to the Empire of America.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Pepsi-Cola is granted a monopoly by the Soviet statist to sell cola, in exchange
 for the Monsieur Henri wines branch of Pepsi selling Russian booze in the
U.S. Monopolies coming and going as the U.S. power elite shows their junior
partners in Moscow how to rake it off. Favors are thrown to the agri-plutocrats
in the form of a grain deal windfall along with cut-rate prices to the properly
humbled Soviet satraps—at U.S. taxpayer expense. Imperium reigns and Pax Americana
 rules the world.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Rumor has it David Rockefeller wants his grandchildren named Julius and
Augustus.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;And, the advanced elements of the Libertarian Party investigates Building
graft in New York City.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;hr /&gt;
&lt;p&gt;1. &lt;em&gt;The Higher Circles&lt;/em&gt; by G. William Domhoff.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;2. &lt;em&gt;None Dare Call It Conspiracy&lt;/em&gt; by Gary Allen.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;3. See A.J.P. Taylor’s &lt;em&gt;The Origins of the Second World War&lt;/em&gt; for what the German
plans actually were in 1939—a leavealone policy in the West and an eventual
gradual push to the East (with Poland as ally!).&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;4. See &lt;em&gt;Revisionist Viewpoints&lt;/em&gt; by James J. Martin.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;5. &lt;em&gt;Our Enemy, the State&lt;/em&gt; (1936) by Albert J. Nook.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;6. Martin, op. cit.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;7. Ibid.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;8. All listed, with references, in Special Revisionism Issue of &lt;em&gt;New Libertarian
Notes&lt;/em&gt; (11), article “U.S. Foreign Policy Towards the Axis.”&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;hr /&gt;
&lt;p&gt;The Southern Libertarian Messenger&lt;br /&gt;
Editor: David Rosinger&lt;br /&gt;
January, 1973 / Vol. I, No. 9&lt;br /&gt;
Pages 3-4&lt;/p&gt;</summary><category term="WWII"></category><category term="war"></category></entry><entry><title>The Libertarian Party, Pro and Con</title><link href="https://www.sek3.net/the-libertarian-party-pro-and-con.html" rel="alternate"></link><published>2015-05-10T00:00:00+08:00</published><updated>2015-05-10T00:00:00+08:00</updated><author><name>David F. Nolan</name></author><id>tag:www.sek3.net,1972-11-01:the-libertarian-party-pro-and-con.html</id><summary type="html">&lt;h2&gt;The Libertarian Party, Pro and Con&lt;/h2&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;em&gt;(Editor’s note: The Libertarian Party had no perceptible effect on the election,
 but its achievement is nonetheless remarkable. Starting from scratch the LP
in a few months grew into one of the movement’s largest organizations, galvanizing
hundreds on the indifferent fringe of libertarianism into activism and attracting
nationwide press coverage.&lt;/em&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;em&gt;(However, the LP has its problems, not the least of which is criticism from
fellow libertarians. In the interest of examining this criticism the&lt;/em&gt; Southern
Libertarian Messenger &lt;em&gt;presents the two letters below. The first is that of Mr.
David Nolan, a founder of the Party and presently its National Chairman, writing
in response to an editorial in the August, 1972&lt;/em&gt; New Libertarian Notes. &lt;em&gt;The second
letter is by Mr. Samuel Edward Konkin III, editor of&lt;/em&gt; NLN, &lt;em&gt;and a leader in the Student
 Libertarian Action Movement and the Libertarian Party Radical Caucus.&lt;/em&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;(The letters form the first part of an exchange of several letters. For one
dollar Xerox copies of the complete correspondence may be obtained from Mr. Konkin
at 635 East 11th Street, Apt. 24, New York, NY 10009.)&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;h3&gt;An Open Letter to SLAM&lt;/h3&gt;
&lt;p&gt;As one of the founders of the Libertarian Party, I found your August issue of
&lt;em&gt;New Libertarian Notes&lt;/em&gt; very interesting, and would like to offer some reactions to
some of the comments therein.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;First, I found your comments on our approach towards achieving Freedom In Our
Time Surprisingly fair, considering the basic differences between your views and
ours. And, while we certainly don’t expect you to agree with everything we’re doing,
 we hope that you will continue to remain “friendly” adversaries, rather than
becoming openly hostile to our efforts, as the LeFevre people have done.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;The differences between LP and SLAM exist, as I see it, on two levels. The
more basic difference, of course, is that you are anarchists, while we are not, at
least for the most part. About 15% to 25% of our members are anarchists, but the
Party as an organization has taken stands that are explicitly anti-anarchist, and
we have no intention of changing our position. (We, too, have our principles.)&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;The secondary difference is one of disagreement over tactics. You tend to
favor a radical, or even revolutionary, approach, while we favor a more moderate,
gradualist approach. Only time will tell which approach is better, and, indeed,
it may be that both have their place. You say that our approach may turn off “revolutionaries”
 and “libertarians evolving from the Left.” And quite possibly this
is so. We counter this point, however, by stating that &lt;em&gt;your&lt;/em&gt; approach will turn
off &lt;em&gt;everyone else. . .&lt;/em&gt; and we think more can be gained, in terms of rolling back
the State, by convincing 51% of the American people to dismantle the State by 49%
than by convincing 1% of the people to dismantle it by 99%.
We don’t ask you to buy this line of reasoning, but point it out simply to show
that there is a consistent rationale behind our methodology, just as there is, no
doubt, behind yours.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;You say, correctly, that anyone who advocates &lt;em&gt;increasing&lt;/em&gt; (or even maintaining)
the current level of State Power is an enemy of freedom. I agree. And the LP certainly
 does not advocate any such thing. We differ from you only in how far, how
fast, and by what means we advocate cutting the State down.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Our 1972 Platform calls nowhere for increasing State Power: in some areas
(such as defense) it simply advocates a change in priorities, but even there, the
net effect would be one of less government action, not more. (Considering our defense
 plank specifically, it should be noted that we call for a strengthened defense
 system for the &lt;em&gt;U.S. only,&lt;/em&gt; while simultaneously calling for a drastic cutback—even
 a virtual elimination—of our commitment to defend other nations. Thus,
while it is true—as &lt;em&gt;National Review&lt;/em&gt; said—that a beefed-up defense system of a
“world policeman” nature would require more spending, the arrangement we advocate
would not.)&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;In most areas, our Platform calls for outright repeal or abolition of government
 activities. In others, merely a substantial reduction. And on balance, it
is—I think you will agree—quite a bit more explicit and “radical” than its predecessor,
 the Temporary Platform. Furthermore, I might point out that if it is not
as “radical” as you might wish, then this is because those who are carping and
bitching the most did not choose to attend the convention at which it was drafted.
We even went so far as to ask the &lt;em&gt;New Banner&lt;/em&gt; to publish a notice urging anarcho-capitalists
 to attend and make their presence felt, but they declined to do so.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;You charge that we will become increasingly statist and compromise-prone as
we grow larger, and that we will put “pressure” on other libertarian organizations
to “serve our interests.” The former allegation is sheer speculation; all evidence
 to date runs counter to it, in fact. As for the latter—just how would we
exert this “pressure,” even if we wanted to? We have no power over any other
group.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;More interesting is the fact that despite your expressed worries on this
point, you do not seem to be against the idea of one libertarian group “pressuring”
another &lt;em&gt;per se,&lt;/em&gt; as you say that SLAM’s “first task” at the moment is “the organization
 of an LP Radical Caucus.” Who is trying to pressure whom?&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;But, in any event, we have no objection to your forming such a Caucus. We
welcome all libertarians into our ranks, and I personally feel that the presence
of a Radical Caucus would be healthy for the Party, if for no other reason than
that it would serve as a counter-pressure to the influence of semi-libertarians
who will no doubt be coming into the Party in increasing numbers, as the GOP and
Democrats become increasingly repulsive. I only hope that when the Radical Caucus
doesn’t always get its own way, it won’t turn around and try to wreck the Party,
thus paying into the hands of the &lt;em&gt;real&lt;/em&gt; enemy—the Nixons and Humphreys of the
world. Fighting our friends—even marginal friends—makes no sense, when there
are so many common foes.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;In any case, good luck, and keep the lines of communication open.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Sincerely,&lt;br /&gt;
David F . Nolan&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;hr /&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Dear Mr. Nolan:&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;I am pleased you find us fair, and hope we shall be found so always. I am
amused of your description of the LeFevre People as “openly hostile,” since they
are well-known pacifists. I do not believe we are secretly hostile, and we are
certainly openly criticized. The two levels you discern are both accurate, and I
am glad to have your admission (openly) that the Party is “explicitly anti-anarchist,
 and we have no intention of changing our position.” I have been trying to
convince several people of that here in New York, and I hope they are willing to
take your word for it.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Indeed, our position, as you state, will turn off everyone else, initially.
We would have liked to have an all-encompassing libertarian alliance to attract
everyone to us for any reason, and have him enter the faction of his taste. As
my editorials point out, your presence has made that option no longer possible,
and, I have analysed, an organization was needed to attract those you must perforce
 leave out. Thus was SLAM resurrected. I hope neither of us will be found
guilty of believing that anyone’s politics are immutable, and that, in fact, our
aims are to both of us to convert (i.e. &lt;em&gt;change&lt;/em&gt;) the positions of the people of
the world to some form of libertarianism, if only in its most fundamental form—leave
 me alone! I find yourself damning by your statistics, in that you wish to
only roll the state back by 49%. When I was a fellow National Office (“trad”)
delegate with you to the 1969 National YAF Convention, I wished to see the elimination
 of 99% of the State’s activities (all but defense and police), and, I am
shocked to see that as I have progressed to advocating the elimination of the
rest, you have actually slid back. As anarchists, we wish to convince as many
people as it takes to eliminate 100% of the state.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Indeed, let us proceed to your Defense plank. &lt;em&gt;National Review&lt;/em&gt;’s argument
was NOT for a “world policeman” nature of defense system in its advocacy of a
beefed-up defense spending, but for the nuclear protection of the continental
United States. You might wish to argue that eliminating the imperialist role of
the U.S. will unleash funds, a fraction of which you would then use for continental
arms increase. I personally do not wish to get embroiled in this kind of argument,
analogous to McGovern welfare economics, but simply submit that, in the given area
for defense of the arbitrarily bounded geographical area called the United States
of America, you would &lt;em&gt;increase&lt;/em&gt; State spending over the level it now occupies. If
not, your angry “semi-libertarian” members may wish to ask you just where you disagree
 with &lt;em&gt;NR&lt;/em&gt;’s defense experts, and I shall leave you to their tender mercies.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;I do not think your taking some of your Temporary Platform positions and making
 them wishy-washy or deliberately ambiguous in the new Platform constitutes radicalizing
 it. As to your implied attack on my “talk, not do,” I suggest you check
your records to find that I was listed as a delegate to your National Convention as
a “representative” for New York. I was unable to travel because of lack of financial
 resources. I am not crying on anyone’s shoulder about it, but I do think
your “carping and bitching” at me is unwarranted. I am delighted to think that you
voted dissolution of the Convention, and reconvened as SLAM, or even LA. While
Colorado is inaccessible to all but rich, hardy, or Coloradan, the State conventions
 coming up should provide the check your hypothesis concerning
 our effectiveness.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;You have already grown more statist by your selecting of John Hospers as your
presidential candidate. According to my source at his Press Conference, Dana Rohrabacher,
 he claimed he was 95% in agreement with conservatives, and when asked by
Dana how he could reconcile his defence and economic positions, Hospers stated that
the economic ones were just theoretical and that he did not expect them to be enacted.
 No longer “sheer speculation,” now stark fact! As to the “pressure” question,
 you should, I suggest, re-read that in context of the Editorial. Clearly,
 I was describing the pressure exerted by your existence, and seeming “success.”
The pressure on activists to defend you when something called “libertarian” is attacked
 in their own circles. The pressure to join one’s nearest ideological neighbors,
 and, if they are in a Party, to participate in these pro-Party activities
they will engage in. And for groups, which will be constantly identified with the
Libertarian Party if the identify themselves as “libertarian,” to either defend
it, or attack it.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;The LP Radical Caucus’s “pressuring” of the Party hierarchy and bureaucracy we
seriously do not expect: the use of us as a counterweight against the Birchers, Objectivists,
 and conservatives in your midst, I do expect. The fundamental task of
LPRC is to reach those people whom, as you earlier pointed out, will not be reached
by SLAM and who can no longer be reached by the defunct LA. In short, we are trying
 to turn on “everyone” who is susceptible to radical libertarianism, however
reaching more. If you wish to set up a “Statist Caucus” in SLAM, feel free.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;The Party will eventually be wrecked, not because we will come in there with
swinging maces, or the archetypical bombs, or even because of our “explosive” rhetoric.
 Not, unhappily, because the State is abolished and it will self-destruct
out of uselessness. No, Mr. Nolan, as I said earlier in passing, we both attend
the St. Louis Convention in 1969. You remained loyal to National Office, while
I, repelled by the injustice and purgings initiated by that group, went over to the
Libertarian Caucus, even though it involved breaking a personal commitment to my
friend, David Keene. You know what state the Young Americans for Freedom is in today.
 So shall be the fate of the Libertarian Party when it begins sacking state
committees and challenging credentials at some convention in the near future to
stop a potential majority of radical libertarians from crystallizing. And there
will be young delegates, like us three years ago, who will be driven to choose, and
in choosing, come to realize the necessary consequences of the opposing philosophies,
 the “ideas that have consequences.” Out of the debacle will arise a new
vigorous anarchist movement in numbers enough to proceed on the Final Organization.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;You can abort this scenario at any point by beginning the purge early. Pass a
prohibition against membership by anarchists, throw those of us who are on State
Committees or other “positions of influence” out before we have a chance to spread.
You can find me in the Executive Committee of the Free Libertarian Party of New
York, awaiting your ax, and you would do me the favour of fulfilling: the prediction
I made to my skeptical colleagues. Of course, you realize what an issue you would
give us. Especially when we evil, horned creatures and “carping, bitching” malcontents
 turn out to be rational and armed with facts and answers to the curious questions
 of the innocent you may have taken into the Party.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Fighting our friends never makes sense, nor even fighting neutrals. Fighting
those within our midst who will deliver us unto our enemies always makes sense. I
am sure you feel the same.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Good luck, David, and I certainly shall keep the lines open. As my friends
know, I would sit down with the devil for a drink and a political argument. Maybe
even Richard Nixon. Definitely David Nolan.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Yours in Freedom,&lt;br /&gt;
Samuel Edward Konkin III&lt;br /&gt;
Editor, &lt;em&gt;New Libertarian Notes&lt;/em&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;hr /&gt;
&lt;p&gt;The Southern Libertarian Messenger&lt;br /&gt;
Editor: David Rosinger&lt;br /&gt;
November, 1972 / Vol. I, No. 7&lt;br /&gt;
Pages 1-5&lt;/p&gt;</summary><category term="LP"></category><category term="LPRC"></category><category term="SLAM"></category><category term="politics"></category></entry><entry><title>A Cram History of the Libertarian Movement. Part II Post-1969</title><link href="https://www.sek3.net/a-cram-history-of-the-libertarian-movement-part-ii-post-1969.html" rel="alternate"></link><published>2015-07-12T00:00:00+08:00</published><updated>2015-07-12T00:00:00+08:00</updated><author><name>Samuel Edward Konkin III</name></author><id>tag:www.sek3.net,1972-10-01:a-cram-history-of-the-libertarian-movement-part-ii-post-1969.html</id><summary type="html">&lt;h2&gt;A Cram History of the Libertarian Movement. Part II Post-1969&lt;/h2&gt;
&lt;h4&gt;Samuel Edward Konkin III&lt;/h4&gt;
&lt;p&gt;The summer of 1969 will be remembered as the sprouting of the modern libertarian
movement. The Objectivists were in turmoil over Branden’s ouster, and many were being
 picked up by Wollstein’s anarcho-objectivist Society for Rational Individualism
(SRI). The seeds of libertarian caucus organization in YAF after the 1967 convention
came to flower in the libertarian takeover of Pennsylvania and California state YAF’s
with Rothbard’s influence putting a few anarchists into the New York State group, and
Karl Hess’s son in Virginia another small group. Many of these Rothbardians, organizing
 into the Radical Libertarian Alliance, attended the SDS National Convention.
Anarchists were being purged before the convention even began, and the group which
had been organized by decentralists, community control advocates and anarchists, ended
 up with nought but the Revolutionary Youth Movement and the Progressive Labor Party,
 not to mention a few Independent Socialists. The first order of business was the
purge of the IS, then the PL. Unfortunately, PL had stacked the Convention too well,
and RYM found itself out-voted. Like good democrats, they rejected the majority decision
 and ran off to grab the National Office files. Each group called itself the
one and only SDS. SDS-RYM promptly split again into RYM-I (Weatherman) and RYM-II
(Bay Area Revolutionary Union, mostly). The RLA and their new friends, the Student
Libertarian Action Movement, went home, with three SDS chapters (including Lysander
Spooner SDS) to add to their disillusioned YAF chapters into RLA. Now, they thought,
for the YAF convention, let us try to organize an Anarchist Caucus. And they did,
writing aboard Karl Hess’s yacht, the &lt;em&gt;Tranquil,&lt;/em&gt; the Tranquil Statement, for enlightenment
 of the YAF average delegate.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;But purges were underway in YAF. First, Wallacism had to go, especially as it
was being succeeded by Willis Carto’s real racism, and Yockeyite neo-nazism. Some
libertarians who supported this action became uneasy when Objectivist chapters were
purged next. Then came the dismissal of the Pennsylvania and California State Offices.
 Needless to say, the libertarians rose up angrily, and Libertarian Caucus mailings
 began to appear across the country with appeals for delegates to overturn the
rulings. In Wisconsin, where David Keene awaited his inevitable succession to the
National Chairmanship (with, I might add, LC endorsement!), the author of this paper
sat blissfully unaware of anything but rumors of malcontents and subversives, and accepted
 a delegate status (as the token Canadian?) with the understanding that Keene
was to be it.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Arriving at St. Louis, Labor Day, 1969, your author was as interested in the St.
Louis World Science Fiction Convention as much as the national YAF convention. But
the meeting with Dana Rohrabacher of California and Don Ernsberger of Pennsylvania,
the ousted LC leaders, instructed one as to the perfidies of the National Office.
The Wisconsin delegation broke, and I and my roommate found our vote for the key Executive
 Committee positions wrested from us through parliamentarianism. We were more
“in” with the establishment than were many of the 100 LCers who lost their credentials
 battles, and regained our votes for the Issues, but by then the votes were_running
 700 to 200 against us. Michael Ingallinera of Virginia, who ran as a “Philosophical
 Anarchist“ received 50, which was the maximum strength of the Anarchist Caucus,
 Rohrabacher got around 250 which was the maximum non-purged LC strength. Then
one of the AC lit a Xerox copy of his draft card before a television camera. The
Traditionalists tried to annihilate him physically, and he was protected by a living
shield of libertarians. Radicalization had set in, and the RLA-SLAM people had found
their mission: &lt;em&gt;agents provacateurs.&lt;/em&gt; Many of us went home, convinced by Keene that
justice would triumph and the splits would be healed. Come 1971, why, we would &lt;em&gt;really&lt;/em&gt;
 be organized.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;The Trads retained control of both California and Pennsylvania, and Ernsberger’s
group joined Wollstein’s SRI to form the Society for Individual Liberty (SIL). The
Rohrabacher wing formed the California Libertarian Alliance,
and Dana travelled around the country, seeding local LA’s with ex-YAFers. Your author
 foundedh the University of Wisconsin LA in late 1969, and the Wisconsin LA the
following summer. Meanwhile, many of us went to New York for the first Libertarian
Conference, held Columbus Day, and featuring Rothbard and Hess.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;But strange things had happened to the Trad speechwriter for Barry Goldwater
who had gone Objectivist, then joined the Constitutional Alliance of Oakley Bramble,
and finally rediscovered the Taftites camped out in New York. Murray Rothbard had
tried to carry the Word in &lt;em&gt;Left and Right,&lt;/em&gt; but finally gave that up for the &lt;em&gt;Libertarian
 Forum&lt;/em&gt; (nee &lt;em&gt;Libertarian&lt;/em&gt;) and Hess became the Washington editor. Hess wrote an
article for &lt;em&gt;Playboy&lt;/em&gt;, “The Death of Politics,” which came to be one of the major recruiting
 tools of the movement. But almost as it was printed, his fascination with
the Leftists that Murray had formed tactical alliances with led him to repudiate
most of it, and attempt to work with the Black Panthers.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;The ex-SDSers and YAFers met each other at the conference and promptly split
into a group which followed Hess into an attack on Fort Dix, and a group which
stayed around to hear Murray discuss economics and Revisionist History. Some of us
were a bit skeptical of our viability at the time, but nevertheless, this author, at
least, became an anarchist at that time. In February, 1970 Dana staged a California
libertarian conference, again “Left-Right,“ which had 500 people and amazing harmony
between anarcho-capitalists and anarcho-communists. Fired up at this success, we
returned to our homes to organize.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Later that year, this author moved to New York—interestingly enough, so did
the action. The RLA, rent by the Hessian defections to the Far Left, began to whither,
 and their &lt;em&gt;Abolitionist&lt;/em&gt; watered itself down until it became the modern wishy-washy
&lt;em&gt;Outlook.&lt;/em&gt; SIL’s &lt;em&gt;Individualist&lt;/em&gt; schedule became more erratic, although their &lt;em&gt;SIL
News,&lt;/em&gt; handled directly by Ernsberger, remained regular. CLA’s venture into slick
publishing, financed by Robert LeFevre’s Rampart College, went two issues as &lt;em&gt;Pine
Tree,&lt;/em&gt; two more as &lt;em&gt;Rap,&lt;/em&gt; and folded. LeFevre, a pacifist “autarhist” began to lose
contributors from his more conservative older followers worried about this influx of,
and support for, long-hairs and weirdos. Rohrabacher has recently returned to activism
 in California and the sagging movement is coming alive again.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Down in Arizona, the Student Libertarian Action Movement was embattled by
street fighting with the State, followed by court cases (which SLAM won). That was
immediately followed by a Split into SLAM and the North American Libertarian Alliance,
 which coughed up two issues of &lt;em&gt;Sunburst,&lt;/em&gt; folded, and was resurrected as a Social
 Revolutionary Anarchist Federation local (SRAF is the Left anarchist grouping).
SLAM devolved to just putting out the &lt;em&gt;Match!,&lt;/em&gt; which Fred Woodworth continues to do.
Meanwhile, in New York, as SIL and RLA waned, Gary Greenberg’s New York Libertarian
Association was joined by this author’s New York Libertarian Alliance, and LA’s were
formed on all Manhattan campuses by early 1972, and several others outside of Manhattan.
 &lt;em&gt;New Libertarian Notes,&lt;/em&gt; originally a pronunciation pun on &lt;em&gt;NYU Libertarian
Notes,&lt;/em&gt; expanded to cover the East Coast movement. Then came the Libertarian Party.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;With the exception of the defeat of the old Preform-Inform crowd’s attempt to
build a new country in the North Sea (which was carved up by Britain, Norway and
Denmark) and their subsequent retreat to nomadism and troglodytism (&lt;em&gt;Vonulife&lt;/em&gt;), no
bigger setback hit the libertarian movement in a decade. The Libertarian Alliance’s
attempt to bring together all libertarians, limited archist or anarchist, left or
right, pro-political party and voting or revolutionary, voter-boycotting, or whatever,
 collapsed. Defections to the Party with the realization that &lt;em&gt;it&lt;/em&gt; and &lt;em&gt;its&lt;/em&gt; positions
 would be identified in the popular mind as what libertarianism was, regardless
of how conservative and statist it was, forced us into an anti-party tactic. First,
an anti-party group was needed to attract people turned off by the Party.
Thus was SLAM reborn in New York. Secondly, a method of reaching the semi-converted
attached to the Party, and exposing them to real libertarianism was needed. At the
moment, organization has begun on a Libertarian Party Radical Caucus. In New York,
the State group has already worked to co-opt us, this
author finding himself on the State Committee/Executive Committee of the Free Libertarian
 Party. LPRC is obviously pictured as analogous to the YAF LC, and it will
be interesting to see if the LP goes in for purges, etc. or some more sophisticated
sell-out and suppression approach.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;This is where you find yourself now. And, as you can deduce, this is where &lt;em&gt;I&lt;/em&gt;
came in!&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;hr /&gt;
&lt;p&gt;The Southern Libertarian Messenger&lt;br /&gt;
Editor: David Rosinger, Editor&lt;br /&gt;
October, 1972 / Vol. I, No. 6&lt;br /&gt;
Pages 3-5&lt;/p&gt;</summary><category term="movement"></category><category term="history"></category></entry><entry><title>A Cram History of the Libertarian Movement. Part I Pre-1969</title><link href="https://www.sek3.net/a-cram-history-of-the-libertarian-movement-part-i-pre-1969.html" rel="alternate"></link><published>2015-06-12T00:00:00+08:00</published><updated>2015-06-12T00:00:00+08:00</updated><author><name>Samuel Edward Konkin III</name></author><id>tag:www.sek3.net,1972-09-01:a-cram-history-of-the-libertarian-movement-part-i-pre-1969.html</id><summary type="html">&lt;h2&gt;A Cram History of the Libertarian Movement. Part I Pre-1969&lt;/h2&gt;
&lt;h4&gt;Samuel Edward Konkin III&lt;/h4&gt;
&lt;p&gt;In the beginning, man was free. Then he ran into his father.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Free philosophies have attempted to form throughout history, usually containing
just enough contradictions or errors to have them refuted and discarded like the statist
 theories they were to replace. Then we came along. The first we goes back to
William Godwin, the first anarchist, in the late 1700’s and traces through Josiah
Warren to Lysander Spooner. The limited government freaks can probably trace their
lineage to Jeremy Bentham’s Philosophical Radical Party in England (yes, dear reader,
the first “radicals” were limited archists), which, thanks to its utilitarian base
and John Stuart Mill, drifted toward Fabian democratic socialism. Meanwhile, back in
the U.S.A., Spooner was firming up a pro-property base for anarchy.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;It is both fascinating to realize (as you will if you read even as little of
Spooner as No Treason) that if Praxeology had been added to Spooner’s position,
amending some of his views on economics, he would have reached the stage of development
 of the present Libertarian Movement, give or take a few deviationists, and dischartening
 to realize that a century has been wasted. This, gentle anarcho-objectivist,
 was all before Ayn Rand was a gleam in her father’s eye. Spooner was an active
abolitionist, shocking his comrades by supporting Southern secession, and demanding
that position as the only one consistent with slave secession from masters. His &lt;em&gt;No
Treason: The Constitution of No Authority&lt;/em&gt; was published around 1870. He, along with
others, passed along the anarchist tradition to Benjamin Tucker, who was the first in
his line to call himself an anarchist from the Word Go.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Tucker also threatened to be the end of the line. His magazine Liberty was recognized
 as &lt;em&gt;the&lt;/em&gt; radical journal until its demise in 1908. George Bernard Shaw acknowledges
 his debt to Tucker for making him famous, and was briefly an anarchist
himself through Tucker’s influence before continuing his meanderings on the political
spectrum through fascism and socialism. Tucker also laid into the anarcho-communists
of his time, setting westerners straight about Bakunin, Kropotkin, and their ilk.
Supposedly, when Tucker met Kropotkin, those attending expected sparks to fly; actually
 they merely exchanged salutations. . .&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;With the onslaught of World War I and the seduction of his radical friends into
what he scourged as “State Socialism,” Tucker despaired of the world and went to
France, dying in obscurity just prior to the Second World war. Some of those he had
influenced were followers of the school of Henry George economics, the “Single Taxers.”
 They believed (and still do) that Rent was immorally obtained, and that Land
should not be owned privately (although anything else could). Some of them believed
that government should at most collect this Rent and distribute it to the populace in
the form of services; a few believed that
this “social function” did not even require
 the state. Such a person was Albert
 J. Nook. Those in his Philosophical
camp around the turn of the century were
called Liberals (so was Herbert Spencer,
whom they were also familiar with), but
became Radicals with World War I and the
split caused by Wilson’s “betrayal” by
entering into war and foreign entanglements.
 Eventually, with the post-war
disillusionment, these Revisionists found
their war interpretation to become widely
 accepted, and during the twenties,
Nock, H. L. Mencken, and others were well-known
 and popular.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;The Depression
and World war II
caused another estrangement
 of these neo-Georgist quasi-anarchists
 with the Liberals; first, because
they opposed Statist
solutions of the Hoover
 and later Roosevelt variety to the
economic problems of
the day, and second,
because they were opposed
 to Roosevelt’s
imperialism against
the Axis and the provocation
 of Japan into a totally avoidable
 war. These positions
 brought them into tactical alliance
 with the Old Right, an uneasy alliance.
 Their influence pervades—the Modern
 Right, as indicated by William Buckley’s
 inclusion of two Nock essays in
his definitive book on conservatism
called, &lt;em&gt;Did You Ever See a Dream walking?.&lt;/em&gt;
 One of Nock’s essays was blatantly
 called “Anarchist’s Progress.” During
 this time, young Georgist Frank
Chodorov was brought into an anti-statist
 position by Nock’s influence, and
became one of the Right’s main activists,
founding the Intercollegiate Society of
Individualists and taking Over Mencken’s
American Mercury along with Buckley and
crowd. About this time, a Young Taft
Republican Columbia student named Murray
Rothbard read von Mises and became an economist,
 studying under the master himself.
The Taft wing or “Old Right” continued
their anti-imperialism through the Korean
war, while the liberals and social democrats
 insisted that Americans had a Duty
to save the world from Bolshevism. In
1953, Robert A. Taft died, unleashing a
Wisconsin Populist named Joseph McCarthy.
Chodorov’s remarks on McCarthyism indicate
the beginning of the end for the alliance:
“The way to get rid of Communists in government
 jobs is to get rid of the government
 jobs.” Unfortunately, William Buckley
 and his converted brother-in-law decided
 that Roman Catholicism was insufficiently
 motivating and
declared a Holy Crusade
against International
Communism. They began
by defending McCarthy
in print, and then, as
&lt;em&gt;American Mercury&lt;/em&gt; fell
into the hands of racists,
 founded &lt;em&gt;National
Review&lt;/em&gt; in 1955 and
staffed it with bitter
ex-Communists. Rothbard, who had made
 friends with many of
these people at the
time, such as &lt;em&gt;NR&lt;/em&gt;’s ideologue, Frank Meyer,
 split with them in 1957
over irreconcilable foreign policy differences, as he Joined SANE
 and various Left peace
(for him, Isolationist)
groups, and the spectrum
flip-flopped. Around
this time the Objectivist philosophy was
turning into the personality cult of Ayn
Rand and Murray was invited to the formative
 get-togethers. Unfortunately, in 1950
he had already decided that the only consistent
 libertarian position was anarchy,
so he knew his days were numbered. Still,
he had some influence on the early Nathaniel
 Branden Institute students.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;In 1960, the New Right got behind Barry
 Goldwater, who symbolized their new synthesis
 of pseudo-free enterprise at home and
American Imperialism abroad. The Youth for
Goldwater became, the following year, a
more ideological youth movement, meeting at
Buckley’s Sharon, Connecticut estate to form
a group of young conservatives. The National Chairman was Bob Schuchman (known to
Rothbard, incidentally) who demanded that the name be the Young Americans for Freedom.
Schuchman was the first and only libertarian Chairman.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;The Goldwater campaign of 1964 brought vast recruits to YAF, and the subsequent
battles with the rising New Left, for which YAF was the only organized opposition,
sustained it in between the election years. Even objectivists began to join it,
though prohibited officially from it by Ayn Rand’s dictates. In 1967, a libertarian
caucus was formed from free market, ISI, and FEE style conservatives, semi-objectivists,
 and a few Rothbardians and even Georgists. They promised to really get it
together in 1969, the next biennial National Convention of YAF.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Meanwhile, Richard Nixon was elected President, fulfilling every conservative’s
dream, and disillusioning every libertarian from his work with the Right, and Murray
Rothbard was into the Peace and Freedom Party, with many of his youthful converts moving
 past him into the SDS, where founders like Carl Oglesby were battling for Anarchy
against the Statist Maoists and Trotskyites who sought control of the group at any
expense. Jarret Wollstein split the Objectivist camp by coming out for anarcho-objectivism
 and the Society for Rational Individualism. And Nathaniel Branden fell from
grace.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;hr /&gt;
&lt;p&gt;The Southern Libertarian Messenger&lt;br /&gt;
Editor: David Rosinger, Editor&lt;br /&gt;
September, 1972 / Vol. I, No. 5&lt;br /&gt;
Pages 1-3&lt;/p&gt;</summary><category term="movement"></category><category term="history"></category></entry></feed>